Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company collection, Inclusive: 1909-1910, undated, Bulk: 1909-1910
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company collection
Inclusive: 1909-1910, undated, Bulk: 1909-1910
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1577
Kelley, Dayton
6 legal-size folders and 1 oversize folder
The Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company collection consists of correspondence, financial notes, clippings, and the articles of incorporation pertaining to the planning and construction of the railroad in 1909-1910. Ultimately, however, the venture failed and the railroad was not completed.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
In 1909, entrepreneurs and investors came together to establish the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company. These three towns were the county seats of McLennan, Bell, and Williamson Counties, respectively, and were all influential markets in the Central Texas cotton trade at the turn of the century.
Backers of the newly chartered railway company sought to build a railroad that would connect Waco to Georgetown in the south with stops at Belton, Ritchie, Moody, Salado, Prairie Dale, and Corn Hill. The railroad was designed to stretch an estimated seventy-five miles with the intention of completely by-passing the town of Temple. Proposals to use portions of the Cotton Belt Railroad to shorten the length of the new railroad were also entertained.
Engineer M.D. Parlin, under the mandate of the Steering Committee, presented the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company with estimates for construction. Upon considering a number of factors, Parlin concluded that the railroad would cost approximately $14,250 per mile of track. Efforts to raise the necessary $75,000 for start-up costs failed, however, and the railroad was subsequently abandoned.
Scope and Content
The materials in the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company collection range in chronology from 1909 to 1910 with some undated materials from that relative time period. It was during these two years that the railway company conducted its initial survey of the line.
Series I. Correspondence consists of letters related to the aforementioned survey. Various correspondents, including Judge G.M. Felts and engineer M.D. Parlin, exchanged letters and reports discussing the logistical aspects of the railroad as well as data related to the towns involved.
Series II. Financial Documents contains a few undated, unidentified balance sheets listing the towns' proposed contributions to the railroad. There are also rosters of some individuals who had been prepared to purchase stocks in the company.
Series III. Literary Productions, the largest series of the collection, is comprised of the company's articles of incorporation, clippings from the Waco Daily Times-Herald, and a rough, hand-drawn sketch of a map detailing the proposed routes and stops of the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railroad. The materials throughout this collection are in average to good condition.
Arrangement
Prior to the current processing, this collection was housed in four folders and organized according to material type. Staff members created an initial box listing when the materials were purchased in 1977. The folders bore descriptions of their contents along with their corresponding date ranges.
The Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company collection has been re-housed into seven folders based on material type. The collection is now arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, and III. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1577. Acquired 1977-03-00
Related Resources
Related references
Long, Christopher. “Belton, TX.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2017 April 24.
Scarbrough, Clara Stearns. “Georgetown, TX, Williamson County.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2017 April 24.
Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company collection, Accession #1577, Box [150], Folders 1-6, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company.
Subjects
Railroads -- Texas -- Belton.; Railroads -- Texas.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.
- Correspondence, 1909-1910; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  The Correspondence Series consists of letters pertaining to the initial survey and gathering of information conducted by the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company. Various correspondents, including Judge G.M. Felts, exchanged letters and reports discussing the financial and logistical aspects of the railroad.
  - Data and Preliminary Survey: Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railroad, 1909-1910 (Box [150], Folder 1)
- Financial Documents, undated; 2
  General condition: Good.
  The Financial Documents Series contains a few undated, unidentified balance sheets listing the towns' proposed contributions to the railroad. There are also rosters of some individuals who had been willing to purchase stock in the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company.
  - Balance Sheets and Rosters, undated (Box [150], Folder 2)
- Literary Productions, 1909-1910, undated; 3
  Series III. Literary Productions contains a variety of materials including the 1909 Articles of Incorporation drafted for the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company. Clippings from the Waco Daily Times-Herald detail the initial progress of the company, particularly the early successes and support it enjoyed among the citizens of Waco. There is also a rough, hand-drawn sketch of a map detailing the proposed routes and stops of the railroad.
  - Article: Waco Daily Times-Herald: "A Committee Will Take It Up Direct", 1910 March 17 (Box [150], Folder 3)
  - Articles of Incorporation: Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railway Company, 1909 (Box [150], Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Waco Daily Times-Herald: Photocopies, 1909 October 22-29 (Box [150], Folder 5)
  - Sketch: Potential Routes of the Waco, Belton, and Georgetown Railroad, undated (Box [150], Folder 6)
  - Clippings: Waco Daily Times-Herald: Originals, 1909 October 22-29 (Box [1022] OVZ, Folder 1)